<chapter id="styles">
  <title>Creating new Styles</title>
  
  <para>It is possible to describe your own bibliography style, by
  writing a simple XML file. The XML file should have the following
  header:</para>

    <programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE bibstyle PUBLIC "-//Pybliographer//DTD Bibliographic Style Format//EN" ""&gt;
</programlisting>
    
  <para>The whole description should fit in a &lt;bibstyle&gt; pair of
    tags, whose  content is shortly  described in this section.  It is
    suggested that the interested users look at the corresponding DTD,
    which describes  the allowed  syntax in details.  This DTD  can be
    found in the same directory as the default style files.</para>

  <sect1 id="styles-global">
    <title>Global formatting</title>
    
    <para>The XML style file describes how the different data fields
      are  organized in  order to  create a  bibliographic  style. For
      example, it can specify that  an article starts with the article
      title  in bold,  followed  by  the authors  names,  etc.</para>
    
    <para>In its current incarnation, the XML format can however not
      describe lower-level informations, like how an author's name
      should be output. This is done by pointing to a set of python
      functions, grouped in a module. Let's consider the following
      example:</para>
    
<programlisting>
  &lt;module name="generic">
    &lt;define field="author">full_authors&lt;/define>
    &lt;define field="editor">first_last_full_authors&lt;/define>
    &lt;define field="date">european_date&lt;/define>
    &lt;define method="keys">string_keys&lt;/define>
  &lt;/module>
</programlisting>

    <para>In this example, we require that the
    <emphasis>author</emphasis> fields should be formatted by the
    <function>full_authors()</function> function, located in the
    <filename>generic</filename> module.</para>

    <para>Such a module has to be declared in the
    <filename>pybrc.py</filename> file, by a line like:

<programlisting>Autoload.preregister ('style','Generic','Pyblio.Style.Generic')</programlisting>
</para>

    <para>The precise definition of the formatting functions is better
    explained      by      looking       at      the      code      of
    <filename>Generic.py</filename> for example.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="styles-definition">
      <title>Bibliography definition</title>
      
      <para>Once the basic formatting definitions have been specified,
      it   is  possible  to   describe  the   aspect  of   the  actual
      bibliographies with following tags:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>	&lt;style name="<varname>stylename</varname>"&gt;</para>

	<para>This tag specifies the current display style, among
	<emphasis>bold, italic, slanted, emph</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>	&lt;inentry name="<varname>entryname</varname>"&gt;</para>

	<para>This tag encloses a block that is only to appear in
	entries of type <varname>entryname</varname>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>	&lt;notinentry name="<varname>entryname</varname>"&gt;</para>

	<para>This tag encloses a block that is only to appear in
	entries that are <emphasis>not</emphasis> of type
	<varname>entryname</varname>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>	&lt;infield name="<varname>fieldname</varname>"&gt;</para>

	<para>This tag encloses a block that only appears when the
	specified <varname>fieldname</varname> field exists in the
	current entry.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>

	<para>&lt;notinfield name="<varname>fieldname</varname>"></para>

	<para>This  tag encloses a  block that  only appears  when the
	specified  <varname>fieldname</varname>  field  <emphasis>does
	not</emphasis> exist in the current entry.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>	&lt;content <optional>name="<varname>fieldname</varname>"</optional>/&gt;</para>

	<para>This empty tag is replaced by the content of the current
	field (when placed in a &lt;infield> block) or the content of
	the field specified as attribute.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>	&lt;separator&gt;</para>

	<para>This tag's content evaluates to nothing when no text has
	been issued so far. It is a convenient way to add a delimiter
	after a series of fields without being worried of the special
	case when the fields are not defined.</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The existing style files are a good source of examples.</para>
    </sect1>

  <sect1 id="styles-future">
    <title>Future of the format</title>

    <para>In the future, this rudimentary format will most likely be
    replaced with an XSL-based mechanism, which should encompass both
    the XML definition and the python modules, thus providing
    standalone style files, parsable by any XSL parser.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

